Guide to the Department of Household Economics and Management records, 1900-1981.
Department of Household Economics and Management records, 1900-1981.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Department of Household Economics and Management records; 1900-1981.
23-18-1789
New York State College of Home Economics. Department of Household Economics and Management.
2.3 cubic ft.
Correspondence, bulletins, photographs, manuscripts, dissertation abstracts, and other documents.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
From its founding until 1969, the department was known as Household Economics and Management; from 1969 to 1977, it was called Consumer Economics and Public Policy; since 1977, it has been the Dept. of Consumer Economics and Housing.
The New York State College of Home Economics is now the New York State College of Human Ecology.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes department correspondence, 1928-1960, primarily letters of Helen Canon; also correspondence of Jean Warren, Edna Van Horn, Dorothy Dickens, Hazel Kyrk, Day Monroe, the Family Economics Division and Family Economics-Home Management Division of the American Home Economics Association. Issues of School of Living Bulletins, 1938-1942; and photographs and other material concerning Mabel Rollins, Lucille Williamson and Jean Warren. Also, thirty-five home account study records from a New York State study conducted by Sally Manning, 1957-1958; 4 volume mss. history "Development of the Department of Economics of the Household and Household Management as Recorded in Documents," 1900-1953; 2 volumes "Schedule Forms," 1929-1960; and 2 volumes of abstracts of Ph.D. theses, Dept. of Household Economics and Management, 1938-1966.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State College of Home Economics. Department of Household Economics and Management.; Canon, Helen, b. 1888.; Dickins, Dorothy.; Kyrk, Hazel, 1886-1957.; Manning, Sally.; Monroe, Day, b. 1888.; Rollins, Mabel.; Van Horn, Edna.; Warren, Jean.; Williamson, Lucille.; American Home Economics Association. Family Economics Division.; American Home Economics Association. Family Economics-Home Management Division.
Titles:
School of living.
Subjects:
Domestic education.; Home economics--Study and teaching.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
The film Within Your Reach from this collection has been digitized and can be found on Cornell's Library Media Space website along with other Home Economics and related films.
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence
  - Course Material, 1943 - 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - History of Household Economics and Management, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Acquiring Old Account Books, 1927 - 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Acquiring Old Account Books, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Acquiring Old Account Books, 1927 - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - Dorothy Dickens, 1945 - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Jean Warren, 1953 - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Edna Van Horn, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - Helen Canon, 1928 - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Helen Canon's Budget and Accounting Information, 1910 - 1934 (Box 1, Folder 10 - 11)
  - Photo, Holiday Cards; Newspaper Clipping and Letter, 1923; 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - School of Living - Suffern, New York, 1929 - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Copies of "School of Living" Bulletins, 1938 - 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Laundry Product - Biz, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Audiocassette - HEM Reunion - with Walker, Rollins, Warren, Stewart, Deacon, Knoll, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- School of Living Bulletins and Newsletter, 1938-1942 (Box 1)
- Photographs and material concerning Mabel Rollins, Lucille Williamson, and Jean Warren, 1981 (Box 1)
- Ralph Borsodi, Flight from the City, The Distribution Age, This Ugly Civilization, Inflation is Coming. (Box 1)
- History of the development of the department as recorded in documents., 1900-1953 (Box 2)
- Forms: Schedule Forms, 1929-1960 (Box 2)
- Abstracts of dissertations, 1900-1966, 1938-1953, 1954-1966 (Box 2)
- Home account books (35 items), 1957-1958 (Box 3)
- Within Your Reach film (Use DVD-1005 in the same box.), F-821 (Box 4)
  Click here to see a digitized version of the film.
  Made in the 1930s, this short film shows the impact of improper kitchen storage on the body and how to design better, more ergonomic storage for the home.
  Produced by the Dept. of Economics of the Household and Household Management Extension Specialists
- Within Your Reach, DVD-1005 (Box 4)